Here we are in our favorite place to be in JupyterLab, ready for some coding and a lot of coding that's
우리가 가장 좋아하는 JupyterLab에 왔습니다 오늘 코딩할 게 아주
going to be today.
많아요
The first thing you may spot, it may have caught your eye that there isn't a day two Jupyter Notebook.
가장 먼저 눈에 띄는 건 둘째 날의 주피터 공책이 없다는 거예요
There are, in fact, five day two Jupyter notebooks, which is a clue that we've got some work cut
5일간 작성된 주피터 공책도 있어요 우리가 할 일이 생겼다는
out for us.
증거죠
And it does also mean that I might be going a bit faster through the notebook than usual, and that's
비트는 제가 평소보다 공책을 빨리 작성할 수도 있다는 뜻이기도
just an opportunity for you to come back and do it yourself and and experiment.
해요 비트가 돌아오면 직접 해 볼 기회가 생기는 거죠
Um, so today we're going to be building a more complex approach to estimating prices of goods, the
오늘은 좀 더 복잡한 접근법을 시도할 거예요 상품 가격 평가법이죠 한동안 해온
same thing we've been working on for a while.
것과 같은 거예요
Um, and the biggest part of today is that we're going to try and approach a rag pipeline solution for
오늘 가장 중요한 부분은 같은 작업을 하기 위한 래그 파이프라인 해결책에
doing the same thing.
접근하는 거예요
Uh, the the intuition is surely this is actually a really great use case for Rag.
직감적으로 봤을 때 랙을 사용하기에 아주 좋은 사례예요
We've got 400,000 prices of products in our training data set.
교육 데이터 집합에 400,000가지 가격이 있어요
Uh, what if we put all of them in a data store, and when we're calling a model, we give it some similar
이것들을 데이터 스토어에 저장하고 모델을 호출할 때 유사한 제품들을 주면서 전동
products and say, hey, please, can you give me the price of this electric toothbrush?
칫솔의 가격을 알려달라고 하면 어떨까요?
And by the way, here are five similar electric toothbrushes from our training data and give that to
훈련 데이터에 있는 유사한 전동 칫솔 5개를 도움될 모델에
a model to help it.
주세요
And it will make total sense to use a frontier model for that.
개척자 모델을 사용하는 게 아주 합리적이죠
And you've got to imagine that armed with some similarities, we're giving a huge head start to the
비슷한 점을 생각해 보면 개척지 모델에서 훨씬 유리하게 출발할 수 있어요. HMSII
frontier model.
HMSI HMSI
And so it is a great example of where rag should shine, because we've got a repository of accurate
래그가 빛나야 할 좋은 예죠 정확한 데이터의 저장소가 있거든요
So it's definitely fits right within the sweet spot.
최적의 조건에 딱 맞아요
So what we're going to do in this notebook, the 2.0 notebook that I'm in right now in the week eight
이 공책에서 할 일은요 지금 제가 있는 0번 공책은 8주 차 폴더인데
folder, we're going to create our vector data store with 400,000 training data points.
400,000개의 훈련 데이터 포인트를 가진 벡터 데이터 저장소를 만들 거예요
So that's a big deal.
그게 중요하죠
That's a lot more than what we did in week five.
5주 차보다 훨씬 많이 했어요
In the next notebook day 2.1.
다음 공책 둘째 날에요 1번요
We're going to visualize it in 2D and then we're going to visualize it in 3D.
2D로 시각화한 다음 3D로 시각화할 거예요
So those are quick notebooks.
빠른 노트들이네요
But it's great to get a hands on sense of these things in day 2.3.
하지만 촬영 2일째에 이런 걸 직접 경험하니 좋네요 Get it 3번요
We're then going to build our Rag pipeline and test it.
그런 다음 래그 파이프라인을 만들어 테스트하죠
And in day 2.4 this is where we do a lot in 1 in 1 notebook.
둘째 날에도요 여기선 공책 하나에 많은 걸 담을 수 있어요
We're going to bring back the random forest processor that we looked at back in week six.
6주 차에 봤던 임의의 산림 처리기를 다시 쓸 거예요
And but we're going to do an improved version of it.
하지만 우린 그걸 개선한 버전을 할 거예요
And then we're going to build what's called an ensemble which which allows all of the models.
그런 다음 앙상블이라는 걸 만들 거예요 모든 모형을 사용할 수 있도록요
Essentially, you can think of it as a sort of voting together.
함께 투표한다고 생각하면 돼요
They're working together on the problem, and it's picking a linear combination of them that is going
함께 문제를 해결하고 선형 조합을 선택해서 최고의 결과를
to give the best results.
내는 거죠
So a lot to get through.
Get up 할 게 많네요
I did want to to mention, look, that we've already built a powerful product processor in the form
말씀드리고 싶은 것은 이미 강력한 제품 프로세서를 특수 LLM의 형태로 만들었다는
of a specialized LLM.
점인데요
So you might be thinking, why are we spending so much time working on this?
왜 이렇게 많은 시간을 투자하는지 궁금하실 거예요
And the answer is simple.
답은 간단해요
It's what I said a moment ago.
방금 제가 한 말이잖아요
This is see this as really about solidifying your expertise.
자신의 전문성을 확고히 하는 과정이라고 생각하세요
We're doing this so you can get more practice with rag.
Get이랑 더 연습하라고 하는 거예요
More practice with other kinds of aspects of building sort of agent based functions, whilst also working
에이전트 기반 함수를 구축하는 다른 양상으로 연습하는 거죠 같은 프로젝트에서 작업하면서요
So we know what we're doing and it's satisfying, and we don't have to curate more data because we have
우린 뭘 하는지 알고 만족스럽죠 데이터가 있으니 더 큐레이팅할 필요가
the data.
없어요
So hopefully that that sort of motivates you for what we're about to do.
그게 우리가 하려는 일에 동기를 부여해주면 좋겠네요
All right, without further ado, we will run some imports environment variables, log in to hugging
좋아요, 그럼 지체 없이 환경 변수를 가져오기 실행할게요 익숙한 얼굴 껴안기로
face stuff we know.
로그인하고요
And I'm going to again I'm going to load in the training data, the pickle file that we have from before
훈련 데이터를 로드하겠습니다 아까 있던 피클 파일이죠 일을 단순화하기
to simplify things just loaded in the training data.
위해 훈련 데이터를 로드했어요
So you may remember we can look at the first of the training data points fuel pump module.
첫 번째 훈련 데이터 포인트 연료 펌프 모듈을 기억하실 거예요
We can call prompts if you remember this.
기억하신다면 프롬프트 호출할 수 있어요
And we will get the familiar prompt that's used for training.
Get Frompts는 훈련에 사용된 익숙한 프롬프트죠
How much this cost to the nearest dollar.
이게 얼마짜리인지 말이에요
And then the price is and the value right there.
가격과 가치가 여기 있네요
Okay.
네
With that time to create our Chroma Datastore.
그동안 크로마 데이터스토어를 만들 거예요
So you may remember back in week five, we created this store with it had 123 documents, if I remember
기억하실지 모르겠지만 5주 차에 이 스토어를 만들 때 123개의 문서가 있었어요
that right, 123 chunks which were taken from our documents, um, of the fictional company ensure ensure
제 기억이 맞는다면 123개의 덩어리가 우리 문서에서 빼냈죠 우리가 사용하도록 보장하는 가상
um, that we used.
회사의 문서였어요
So this time we're going to create a chroma datastore with 400,000 documents.
이번엔 400,000개의 문서가 있는 크로마 데이터스토어를 만들 거예요
That's a lot.
많네요
We're not going to chunk it up.
부수지 않을 거예요
Of course we don't need to.
당연히 안 해도 되죠
These are already small chunks.
이미 작은 조각이에요
Each each product is going to go in chroma as its own item.
각각의 제품은 각각의 아이템으로 채도에 들어갈 거예요
Um, so, uh, we're not going to be using Lang chain for this rag pipeline because it's good for us
이 랙 파이프라인에는 랑체인을 쓰지 않을 거예요 직접 만드는
to, to actually build it ourselves.
게 더 좋거든요
Uh, Lang chain gives some good, useful abstractions, but it's not necessary.
랑 사슬은 유용한 추상적 개념을 제공하지만 꼭 필요한 건 아니에요
And once you get to the level of proficiency that you are now at, you can just be working directly
현재 수준에 이르면 그냥 LIms로 작업하면
with Llms often you won't need necessarily these these sorts of abstraction layers built on top of it.
됩니다. 이런 추상화 계층이 꼭 필요하진 않아요.
Um, so that's what we're going to do.
그렇게 할 거예요
Uh, so we are going to create a chroma database, and I called it somewhere up here, I think.
채도 데이터베이스를 만들 거예요 여기 어디쯤에 호출했죠
Um, I might have taken that constant out earlier.
그 상표는 아까 뺐을 거예요
Let's do that right now.
지금 당장요
Apologies.
미안해요
Uh, we will add in here another constant DB equals products underscore vector store.
여기에 다른 상수 DB = 제품_벡터 스토어를 추가할게요
I was cleaning up this notebook to make it useful, and I cleaned it up too much.
쓸모 있게 쓰려고 이 공책을 치우다가 너무 많이 치웠어요
Uh, if I spelled that right, I have products.
철자가 맞는다면 상품이 있어요
Vector store.
벡터 스토어요
There we go.
됐어요
All right, so back we go.
다시 돌아가죠
Momentary diversion.
잠시 우회한 거죠
So we're going to create a chroma data store with that path.
그 경로로 크로마 데이터 저장소를 만들 거예요
There we go.
됐어요
We're going to check if it exists and delete it if it does already exist.
존재하는지는 확인하고 이미 존재한다면 삭제하죠
I'm not going to run that.
그건 안 할 거예요
It will delete this products vector store which I have created.
제가 만든 벡터 스토어를 삭제할 거예요
And which takes a little bit of time.
비트를 만드는 데 시간이 좀 걸려요
Uh, although not that much time, but.
그렇게 오래는 아니지만요
But I will let you run this yourself.
하지만 직접 운영하게 해드리죠
So we are going to use a new a different type of embedding.
그래서 새로운 유형의 엠베딩을 사용할 거예요
We are going to use something called the sentence transformer.
문장 변압기라는 걸 사용할 거예요
It's a useful model from hugging face it maps text chunks to 384 dimensions.
얼굴을 감싸는 유용한 모델로 텍스트 덩어리를 384차원으로 매핑하죠
Um, and it's ideal for things like semantic search.
시맨틱 검색 같은 것에도 이상적이죠
It's a transformer model that produces these vector embeddings.
벡터 내장 기능을 만드는 변압기 모델이죠
You may remember we used OpenAI embeddings when we built our Rag pipeline before.
예전에 랙 파이프라인을 만들 때 오픈AI 엠디딩을 사용했던 걸 기억하시나요?
So if you compare the two of those together, this hugging face one, uh, it's it doesn't have the
그래서 이 두 가지를 함께 비교해 보면 서로 껴안는 얼굴 1번은 입체감이
same dimensionality.
달라요
So and it's probably not as accurate as the OpenAI embeddings one.
오픈AI의 삽입 방식만큼 정확하진 않을 거예요
But it's free, it's fast and we can run it locally.
하지만 무료에 빠르고 로컬에서 실행할 수 있죠
And that last point is super important because there are some cases where you might not want the data
마지막 포인트는 아주 중요합니다 왜냐하면 어떤 경우에는 데이터가 박스를 떠나지 않기를
to leave your box.
원할 수도 있거든요
For example, if you're working on that project I assigned you from week five and you're looking to
예를 들어, 제가 5주 차에 배정했던 프로젝트를 작업하고
build your own personal Rag database with your own stuff like your emails and things.
있다면 이메일 같은 것으로 개인 랙 데이터베이스를 구축하고 싶을 거예요
You might not want to send them all to OpenAI, even though it should be safe, you just might prefer
안전한 방법이지만 오픈라이로 보내지 않고 직접 보내는 게 나을 수도 있습니다
to do it yourself, and this is an easy way to do it without it leaving your box.
이렇게 하면 상자에서 꺼내지 않고도 쉽게 전송할 수 있죠
So we load in that model from hugging face.
안는 얼굴에서 모델을 로딩해요
It gives a warning that I think we can ignore about in the future, that something will have to be set
이 경고는 무시해도 될 것 같아요 미래에는 뭔가 달라져야 한다는
differently.
경고죠
Um, so what you can then do once you've created this model is you can call model dot encode.
이 모델을 생성하고 나면 Model.in코드를 호출할 수 있어요
You pass in a list of text documents.
텍스트 문서 목록을 제출해요
What you'll get back is a numpy array.
NFF 배열을 얻게 될 거예요.
And you can just I can pluck the first one out of that and I will get my vector.
첫 번째 것을 뽑고 벡터를 get 할 수 있어요
And it was pretty quick.
꽤 빨랐어요
And it works well in bulk as well.
대량으로 사용해도 효과적이죠
So if we if we look at the length of this vector we will see it's got 384 dimensions to it.
이 벡터의 길이를 보면 384차원인 걸 알 수 있어요
We can just print it and we'll see.
일단 출력해서 보죠
It will be a big old vector.
거대한 벡터가 될 거예요
There it is.
저기 있네요
So that vector in some way represents well hi there in numbers in a way that is a multi-dimensional
벡터는 어떤 식으로든 숫자로 나타내는데 LM에 따라 다차원적인
reflection According to the LM.
반사로 나타나죠
So that is, uh, is worth, uh, um, playing with and getting a sense of it.
그래서 한번 해 보고 감을 잡아 볼 가치가 있어요
So what I'm now going to do is write this utility method description that takes an item, one of our
이제 이 유틸리티 메서드 설명을 작성하겠습니다 항목 하나를, 우리 항목 중
items, and turns it into just a chunk of text.
하나를 그냥 텍스트 덩어리로 바꾸는 거죠
So if I run that just to show you, if you remember, if we look at something like the first training
보여드리기 위해 실행해 볼게요 기억하실지 모르겠지만 첫 번째 트레이닝 포인트
point and we look at its prompt, that's what the prompt looks like.
같은 걸 보고 프롬프트를 보면 프롬프트는 이렇게 생겼어요
If instead of that I now call description on that item, I just get the same thing, but without the
만약 그것 대신에 해당 항목에 대한 설명을 호출하면 같은 것이 나오지만 앞에 있는 것들 없이
stuff at the front and without the price, it's just a description of the product on its own.
가격 없이요. 그냥 제품에 대한 설명만 있는 거에요.
And what we now do is we go and put that into our vector data store.
이제 벡터 데이터 저장소에 Put을 할 거예요
So we run that code and it will take a while.
코드를 실행하면 시간이 좀 걸려요
And by the time it's finished, it will be in the vector data store and you'll be ready for business.
완료될 때쯤엔 벡터 데이터 저장소에 있을 테니 여러분은 준비가 된 거죠
I've already run it, so it's already created my vector data store.
이미 실행했어요 벡터 데이터 저장소가 이미 생성됐죠
You can see over on the left.
왼쪽을 보시면 돼요
You should do that now.
지금 하세요
And when you're done, I will see you for the next video.
다 끝나면 다음 영상에서 만나요